Yesterday,
I stumbled across a quite interesting
video on YouTube, and since I
was mentioned in that video
and was called out, I thought, well,
I'll just react
to it.
The video is called No one watches YouTube
course,
I'll put a link below this episode.
It's by Melkey, Melkey, uh, I don't know.
But I don't have to pronounce him
correctly because he did not pronounce,
correctly either. And in this video,
he argues that there
are no coding tutorials out there anymore,
and I can definitely relate and I'll
share my thoughts on that.
But let's first, uh, hear what he has to
say.
You see, when I was learning,
I would rely heavily on channels like
or Ben Awad, or even this individual,
Maximilian, uh,
Schwarz Mueller.
I won't even pronounce his name,
Yeah, it's Schwarzmuller,
and I think it's a super easy name in
so I don't know why you did not get this
right.
Where he made a lot of courses on stuff
like Udemy about
React and other things, and so did Ben
and so did Traversy.
And now if you look at their channels,
you will see something very different.
And the major thing on Traversy Media's
channel now is learning to code has
changed,
where he goes into detail of why things
have drastically changed for new junior
developers
or even just people on their approach to
learning how to code.
And you can even see through his channel,
there's not that many
crash course or tutorial videos.
It's coding before AI was in the Stone
Age.
The junior developer will look different
It's a bunch of different things where
it's people explaining their
tech stack, their decision,
and just giving their opinions on certain
tech-related topics.
Ben Awad doesn't even make videos
anymore,
so he's just no longer doing this.
Um, this individual, Maximilian,
if you go to his channel and you go to his
videos,
there's absolutely no more tutorial videos
because they don't generate views because
people no longer watch
that type of content.
Yep. And that's exactly the point,
but again, I'll share more thoughts
on this. He's absolutely right though.
Of course coding tutorials have had better
times,
let's be totally honest. Now,
I will say that on
this very channel,
if you're watching this on YouTube,
was founded,
I created this channel to share my
opinion. The channel where I used to
share tutorials is the Academind channel,
but of
course, let's be honest,
if you take a look at this channel, it
has seen better days with more activity.
I'll be totally honest,
and you have to scroll down quite a bit
to see those old school tutorials there.
Now, I have some plans for this channel.
I'll share them.
And I, uh, don't just have plans.
I already got some, I think,
exciting new tutorials lined up on this
channel, but
still, tutorials, coding tutorials
and maybe also
tutorials in general are maybe not
dead, but they might be dying
or they definitely had better
days. And just to be clear, you still have
plenty of high quality coding tutorials
out there.
I mean,
you've got Code With Antonio with his
courses essentially, though, um,
if you take a look at those view
numbers, the question is if it's worth it,
but that is for him to
decide, but you definitely got him.
You will find high quality tutorials on
Python, any coding, uh, language
or programming language
you, uh, are interested in, obviously.
You got FreeCodeCamp, though there too,
you can see
those view numbers
are not necessarily what they used to be.
And one trend I think you can see
is all these coding tutorials are more and
more becoming super low level,
even more low level
than they've always been. There
is very little
demand for advanced content,
and they're all
about entertainment, to some degree at
least. You have those projects
where people just,
it feels like they wanna watch you build a
project.
They don't really wanna learn how to build
project. So it all got a bit more
entertainment-ish and
project focused, which of course
is something I
could also do and Brad could also do.
Just the content we created
doesn't really vibe anymore, and I think,
for example,
if you take a look at those numbers on
fair to say that coding tutorials in
general don't perform that well anymore
and are definitely not on the level they
used to be in
the past. And I think there
are three main reasons
for that, and the first one is TikTok
or short form
content in general. You see,
TikTok of course, I had to look this
up because I'm not a TikTok user,
but TikTok was introduced
in 2016 as it seems, nine years ago.
Quite a long time,
but it really only took off
for me or that I really heard about it
and people around me
started using it in I think
2018-ish, 2019, and then of course
with the pandemic I would guess,
and of course nowadays
it's all short form content.
All the videos have to be short
form. And of course it's not just TikTok,
you know that, but TikTok has pretty
impressive numbers.
Two billion global users.
That's so much wasted time, really.
So much wasted time. Uh,
two billion global users just
on TikTok, if you can trust the Google AI
overview here.
And then of course it's not just TikTok.
It's also Instagram Reels, YouTube Shorts,
for
example. YouTube Shorts alone, uh,
exceed more
than 70 billion views every day. Again,
so much
wasted time and...By the way,
there definitely also
are good shorts. I'm not doubting that.
And I have created shorts myself
and I'll try to create
more because simply that
is what people watch and if they watch it,
least try to create something that's
helpful. Um, at least I can...
Well, I can try. But yeah,
it's so much consumption.
Two billion monthly active users, uh,
on YouTube.
Um, it's, it's, it's really mind-blowing.
So yeah, shorts are there,
attention spans got shorter and
that of course has
implications.
If you take a look at my channel here,
the same if you take a look at Brad's
channel, uh, or other coding tutorial
channels, if you scroll down,
if you go back a couple of years,
you will see that, um... Let's see,
this one here is
around 2020, so right
when the pandemic hit of course.
And if you take a look at those numbers,
sure, there are some
weaker vid- videos, also some videos
were just announced stuff, but overall
got pretty good consumption on most of
these videos.
And most of these videos
are good old tutorial videos
where I simply share certain
approaches, tips and tricks, teach stuff,
right?
So we got amazing consumption.
If you scroll down even
further, if you go back to, uh,
I think around 2018,
'19, back then I used to be able to
create series where you would
have, um, one topic, uh, for example here,
Node and, and
GraphQL,
and I would create a bunch of videos on
And sure,
every video on its own would probably only
20,000 views, or maybe
when I released them just 5 to
15,000 and then over time they gathered up
those views.
But of course those
were easy to produce and I was
able to show a, a kind of real
project. I was able to dive deep.
That's the main takeaway because
all these videos were half an hour long.
That's essentially a free course I
published on
YouTube.
And the entire course of course did get
quite a lot of views as you can see.
And then you had those
single videos, um,
where you talked about one specific
topic, a-
and you got a lot of views on that too.
And I'll be very honest, I loved that
time, um, because sharing knowledge
is what I
love. I,
I think I'm also good at it hopefully,
what I enjoy. I, you know,
I learned it all on myself, the coding
stuff. I mean, I did not study that.
I studied business, uh, administration.
Um, but I started to code when I
was around 12, 13, something like
that.
And back then of course without the
learned to code by reading books,
by just trying out stuff.
I do remember that one of my first
projects when I was,
well, 13 or so, was to build my
own documentation written with raw HTML
and CSS
for Warcraft III.
And I know not programming languages,
point. So that is where I'm coming from.
I do enjoy sharing knowledge and yeah,
that was what you could do back then.
By the way,
back then I also already had these opinion
developer and they did great too,
and that's why I created this channel here
I wanted to just share opinions because of
course, you know, YouTube changed.
YouTube changed.
Back then you could have it all in one
Subscribers were very important.
Um, nowadays subscribers
are a nice number, but it's
all about grabbing attention,
making it through or into the
YouTube algorithm
and therefore of course you got to have
challenge, uh, channels.
You have one channel for your opinions,
one channel for your livestream VODs,
one channel for your
tutorials.
That is how it seems to work these days
and you get kind of punished
if you don't do it like this.
That's also why you got the face on all
these thumbnails, though I can see I
already d- did that back then.
But nowadays it's even more important.
You got to look shocked on those
thumbnails, um, or, or something
attention-grabbing. So yeah, that
is the current state.
And this, by the way,
just to be very clear, is not...
I'm not saying this to, to whine about it.
Yeah, I do miss it. I,
I liked those old days, but I'm getting
older, right? So that,
that's just what it is, but I accept that
things changed and I of course try to
change with that, which
is why this channel here has quite a lot
of
activity and why I'm struggling with this
Academind channel is
as you can see if you scroll up. And
if you scroll up, you can see those
videos, those tutorial videos here,
like this Remix Crash Course, yeah,
130,000 views. It's a lot but this
was released it says
three years here,
it's almost four years ago I think, um, or
it might be three years. But this
is the number over three years
some videos here like these AWS videos
which were a lot of effort
which don't even have 10,000 views after
three years.
And these actually are almost four years.
So you see those numbers are declining for
the good old tutorials and, uh,
one reason is
definitely the attention spans.
But that's of course not the
only reason.
The other big reason I think is
macroeconomics. You might know this chart
here, this quite depressing chart, uh,
which shows
the software development job postings on
Indeed in the United States.
So not worldwide, not all platforms,
but still it
kind of... It,
it shows what it feels to us, right?
So you can see we, we had
that huge high during the
pandemic and unfortunately the chart
doesn't go back any further than the
early 2020s. Uh, so, uh, February 2020.
So we don't really have a lot of
pre-pandemic data in there
came from here. Then we had a drop
when the pandemic hit and then we, whoa,
we s- we shot up to high, uh,
spheres.... the pandemic, of course, not.
But that time was amazing from the
perspective of a content creator because,
of course, everybody was learning to
code. So creating courses, which I do,
which I still do, and which I'll keep
on doing, by the way,
that worked really well.
But also, on YouTube,
you got a lot of attention.
Still, of course,
we still had the effects from the, uh,
span and TikTok and so on, but
that made more than up for
it. And then things changed,
and that's not
AI, by the way. Here we,
we started declining before
ChatGPT was released.
So we went down steeply because
companies over-hired. During the pandemic,
everybody thought that this is the
new normal and, um, w-
we'll need like five times
the software engineers forever,
and it turned out that's not the case.
And it's not just in web development,
it's software development in general.
It's also in game development,
for example.
Um, if you're a gamer,
I am to some degree, um,
of studios that got closed or that
are struggling.
So it's a, a software development
crisis, you could say. Now,
at least it looks like we now hit
the bottom, um, but of course, um, yeah,
we still got that
AI thing and I'll get back to that. Um,
but that is, of course,
one other major factor.
The demand for these tutorials obviously
decreased. And combine
that with the effect of shorter attention
spans and those long-form tutorials not
working that well,
that's just another hit. And then,
of course, we have
AI as the large third main
reason here. And by the way,
just a little shameless plug, I created
this graphic here just by drawing it here
in this ugly
form on Excalidraw,
but I could've also used a piece of paper.
And then I went to my site,
buildmygraphic.com, and there I chose
custom content, selected photo,
uploaded that, uh, drawing,
and added some little extra instructions.
Picked my preferred style, watercolor,
and generated
this graphic.
So if you also need some graphics,
other kinds of graphics,
you might wanna give that a try.
I'll put a link below the video. But AI,
that
is the third main reason, and, of course,
it started
slow in November 2022 when
ChatGPT was released, but obviously, AI
is a huge
thing right now and it affects basically
all aspects
of life and learning,
and online learning is definitely one of
them. Why watch a 30-minute tutorial
if you
can just ask ChatGPT? Well, there
are good reasons why you
might wanna watch a tutorial,
because there is a difference between
for something and possibly getting AI
hallucinations or
outdated information.
And on the other hand, having someone
guide you through a topic you might not
even know already.
But of course, I still get the point
and I do it myself.
We can learn rapidly or at least
feel like we're learning to some extent
with ChatGPT
or Gemini,
or whatever your favorite AI chatbot is.
And of course, there are advantages,
because you can ask just the follow-up
questions you have.
If you're watching a tutorial
something, you're kind of out of luck.
You have to do your own research, which,
by the way, (laughs) is not necessarily
bad, but that's a different story.
But of course, yeah,
it's more convenient
result quicker if you can just ask.
Let's be totally honest though,
is ChatGPT really that great for
learning or is it good for getting
results? Just as you can use Cursor
or Claude
code for agentic engineering, so as
assistants, or for vibe coding or kind of
vibe coding. One of the two is more work.
You can use ChatGPT for learning, but
that involves
thinking about the responses,
still doing your own research,
trying out stuff,
coming up with smart follow-up
questions, diving deeper,
reading official documentations from time
time. It's complex,
and it always will be to some
extent because these tools can make it
easier, but learning is all
about wiring up those neurons.
That doesn't come for
free. But of course, it
is super convenient to just ask for
something, get a solution, use it,
and move on.
And to be fair, we did
that even before ChatGPT with Stack
Overflow in certain situations.
But of course, ChatGPT and those other
chatbots have drastically accelerated all
of
that. And that kind of brings us to
today and the current situations.
All these factors are the reasons why
no one watches YouTube to learn anymore,
and
why all these channels, including mine,
have kind of
slowed down or entirely stopped in
releasing coding
tutorials. And of course,
I know there will be people that say,
"That's no problem. Tutorial hell
was awful anyways,
and you just all create BS content." And
yeah, sure, haters gonna hate.
There will always be people
you do, and obviously,
it's also gotten worse on YouTube
internet because people
are just so unhappy in the world,
But I get the point, of course,
you could end up
in tutorial hell.
You could watch tutorial after tutorial
and never get anything done. Learning
is and was
always about applying what you learned.
If you watch a tutorial,
if you gain some knowledge, it
that in some demo project,
in a real project, whatever it
is. Now with ChatGPT and all these AI
chatbots,
you have the stupidity hell problem
that you just ask for something,
get a solution, never really question it,
understand it, and move on. And well,
your skill level
will essentially be the skill level of the
AI because you got no
skill on your own, and I'm not sure
if that is a
better world. Obviously,
you can use AI to learn and to
question things,
and then it can be an accelerator, as I
said. But I think the best learning
today...... would be still to have
that mixture of
human input, human guidance, getting that,
that opinion
mixed into what you're learning,
getting that extra
experience,
those little side quests on which I
sometimes, uh,
went in my tutorials where I explain
something related or explain why we're
doing something in a certain way
instead of just giving you the solution
because that's also
important. Depending on how you prompt AI,
you might never hear about
alternatives.
You might just get a solution
but it might not be.
So for all these reasons, I think
there is value in human guided learning,
and that of course
includes YouTube tutorials,
just as it includes
blog articles, books, audio formats,
whatever it is for you. It
is a mixture and I'll
work heavily also in the next year on
finding
better solutions for this blended learning
approach, and I'll
share more about that once I'm ready to.
I got some great ideas, I think. But yeah,
I do
miss those old days. It just doesn't help.
It's, uh, it's a new world in
which we're living now
and we have all these factors, and
let's be very honest,
probably all three factors are
just going to accelerate. I mean,
the macroeconomics only indirectly
influenced by AI but people
are watching short form
content and I don't, I don't see
that going away.
And AI is also here to stay. AI
is not going away, obviously, and
it... By the way, just to make
that very clear, it is useful and
everything. You know that
if you watch my videos,
I'm using AI heavily, but of course,
it's having impacts and it's
having a lot of negative downsides,
which I also regularly talk
about. Um, so yeah, I
wholeheartedly agree with everything
Melkky Melkay said
in this video. I recommend watching it,
and
I think we'll just have to adjust,
and I'll definitely try to do that.
I'll keep on creating educational content
on Academind as well.
I got some nice tutorials, actually one
full course for free lined up on
that channel.
I got plenty of ideas. Time
is the only issue.
And yeah, I'll share more once I'm ready.
Definitely please also share what you're
thinking of all of that.
What are your thoughts on this
or what did I maybe
miss?